<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902"   category="std"
     docName="draft-ietf-bmwg-network-tester-cfg-12" >
    <front>
    <title abbrev="NETWORK-TESTER-MANAGEMENT-11">A YANG Data Model for Network Tester Management</title>
    <author initials="V" surname="Vassilev" fullname='Vladimir Vassilev' >
      <organization>Lightside Instruments AS</organization>
      <address>
        <email>vladimir@lightside-instruments.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
    <workgroup>Benchmarking Working Group</workgroup>
    <abstract>
        <t>
This document specifies a YANG data model for use in network interconnect testing setups that contains instances of traffic generator and traffic analyzer.
        </t>
    </abstract>
</front>
<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
    <t>
There is a need for a standard mechanism for specification
of the transactions part of network tests and their implementation
over standardized network management protocols.
Such a mechanism should allow the control and monitoring of the data plane traffic in a transactional manner.

This document defines a YANG <xref target="RFC7950"/> data model which is composed of two YANG modules for test traffic generator and analyzer functions.
    </t>
<section anchor="problem" title="Problem Statement">
    <t>
Network interconnect tests require active network
elements part of the tested network that generate
test traffic and network elements that analyze
the test traffic at one or more points of its forwarding path.

A network interconnect tester is an entity that can either
generate test traffic, analyze test traffic, or both.

Figure 1, borrowed from <xref target="RFC2544"/>,
represents the horseshoe test setup topology consisting
of a single tester and a single Device Under Test (DUT) connected in a
network interconnect loop.

        <figure>
            <name>Test setup with tester that both sends the test traffic and receives it back</name>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                 +------------+
                 |            |
    +------------|  tester    |<-------------+
    |            |            |              |
    |            +------------+              |
    |                                        |
    |            +------------+              |
    |            |            |              |
    +----------->|    DUT     |--------------+
                 |            |
                 +------------+

            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

This document defines a YANG data
model of a network interconnect tester that can be used for
development of vendor-independent network interconnect tests
and utilize the advantages of transactional management using
standard protocols like Network Configuration Protocol
(NETCONF) <xref target="RFC6241"/>.

    </t>
<section title="Objectives">
    <t>
This section specifies the design objectives for the data model. It should:

<list style="symbols">
  <t>provide means to specify the generated traffic as streams of cyclic sequence of bursts with configurable frame size, frame data, interframe gap and interburst gap.</t>
  <t>have a mandatory single stream mode and optional multi stream mode.</t>
  <t>provide means for configuration of traffic streams with static frame data where frames with identical frame data are sent during the lifetime of the stream.</t>
  <t>provide means for configuration of traffic streams with dynamic frame data where frames contain fields with dynamic data like generation time and sequence number.</t>
  <t>allow third parties to augment the base modules with alternative dynamic fields of frame data extensions.</t>
  <t>provide means for realtime synchronization and orchestration of the generated streams.</t>
  <t>provide counters for received test traffic frames and octets.</t>
  <t>provide latency statistic in the case of test traffic with dynamic frame data that includes timestamp.</t>
  <t>provide sequence number errors in the case of test traffic with dynamic frame data that includes sequence number.</t>
  <t>provide means for capturing traffic frames data.</t>
</list>
    </t>
</section>
</section>     
<section anchor="data_model_overview" title="Data Model">
<section anchor="overview" title="Overview">     
    <t>
The data model splits the design into two YANG modules - (1) Traffic
Generator module (TG) and (2) Traffic Analyzer module (TA). The modules are
implemented as augmentations of the "ietf-interfaces" <xref target="RFC8343"/>
module adding configuration and state data that model the
functionality of a network interconnect tester.  The TA and TG modules concept is
illustrated with the diagram depicted in Figure 2 with a tester with two interfaces (named "eth0" and "eth1") connected in a loop with single DUT.

        <figure>
            <name>Test setup where TG and TA modules are colocated on the same entity</name>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                 +----------------+
     eth0.egress |                | eth1.ingress
    +------------| TG  tester  TA |<-------------+
    |            |                |              |
    |            +----------------+              |
    |                                            |
    |              +------------+                |
    |              |            |                |
    +------------->|    DUT     |----------------+
                   |            |
                   +------------+

            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
The data plane model used is of a sequence of octets that are either part of a frame or a gap.
The gaps consist of octets that are idle and octets that are used for lower level protocol framing.

The TG module can configure deterministic cyclic or finite sequence of static and dynamic frames.

For example an implementation of a dynamic test frame could
have the last 18 octets of the payload of the generated
frames contain incrementing sequence number field
(8 octets followed by timestamp field in the
<xref target="IEEE1588"/> format (10 octets). If frame data is defined
for the last 18 octets of the payload, it will be ignored
and overwritten with dynamic data according to this
specification. In addition a dynamic payload can fill
the remaining available space in the frame.
    </t>
</section>
<section title="Using the Network Interconnect Tester Data Model">
<t>
  A basic example of how the data model can be used in transactional network test program to control the testers part of a network and report counter statistics and timing measurement data is presented in <xref target="examples"/>.
  All example cases present the configuration and state data from a single test trial. One of the examples demonstrates the use of the <xref target="RFC2544"/> defined test frame packet.
  The search algorithm logic that operates to control the trial configuration is outside the scope of this document.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Traffic Generator Module Tree Diagram" anchor="traffic-generator-module-tree-diagram">
<t>
  The meaning of the symbols in the YANG tree diagrams are defined in <xref target="RFC8340"/>
        <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
module: ietf-traffic-generator

  augment /if:interfaces/if:interface:
    +--rw traffic-generator!
       +--rw (type)
       |  +--:(single-stream)
       |  |  +--rw testframe-type?     identityref
       |  |  +--rw frame-size          uint32
       |  |  +--rw frame-data?         binary
       |  |  +--rw gap      uint32
       |  |  +--rw burst-gap?     uint32
       |  |  +--rw frames-per-burst?   uint32
       |  |  +--rw modifiers
       |  |     +--rw modifier* [id]
       |  |        +--rw id             uint32
       |  |        +--rw action         identityref
       |  |        +--rw offset         uint32
       |  |        +--rw mask           binary
       |  |        +--rw repetitions    uint32
       |  +--:(multi-stream)
       |     +--rw streams
       |        +--rw stream* [id]
       |           +--rw id                   uint32
       |           +--rw testframe-type?      identityref
       |           +--rw frame-size           uint32
       |           +--rw frame-data?          binary
       |           +--rw gap                  uint32
       |           +--rw burst-gap?           uint32
       |           +--rw frames-per-burst?    uint32
       |           +--rw frames-per-stream    uint32
       |           +--rw stream-gap           uint32
       |           +--rw modifiers
       |              +--rw modifier* [id]
       |                 +--rw id             uint32
       |                 +--rw action         identityref
       |                 +--rw offset         uint32
       |                 +--rw mask           binary
       |                 +--rw repetitions    uint32
       +--rw realtime-epoch?
       |        yang:date-and-time {realtime-epoch}?
       +--rw start-delay?              uint64
       +--rw total-frames?             uint64
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
</t>
</section>
<section title="Traffic Analyzer Module Tree Diagram" anchor="traffic-analyzer-module-tree-diagram">
<t>
        <figure>
             <artwork><![CDATA[
module: ietf-traffic-analyzer

  augment /if:interfaces/if:interface:
    +--rw traffic-analyzer!
       +--rw testframe
       |  +--rw type?     identityref
       |  +--rw filter! {testframe-filter}?
       |     +--rw type      identityref
       |     +--rw mask?     binary
       |     +--rw data?     binary
       |     +--rw offset    uint32
       +--rw capture! {capture}?
       |  +--rw max-frames-visible?       uint64
       |  +--rw max-frame-data-visible?   uint32
       |  +--rw start-trigger!
       |  |  +--rw (start-trigger)
       |  |     +--:(frame-index)
       |  |     |  +--rw frame-index?       uint64
       |  |     +--:(testframe-index)
       |  |        +--rw testframe-index?   uint64
       |  +--rw stop-trigger!
       |  |  +--rw (stop-trigger)
       |  |     +--:(when-full)
       |  |        +--rw when-full?   empty
       |  +--rw filter! {capture-filter}?
       |     +--rw type    identityref
       +--ro state
          +--ro statistics
          |  +--ro pkts?          yang:counter64
          |  +--ro octets?        yang:counter64
          |  +--ro idle-octets?   yang:counter64 {idle-octets-counter}?
          |  +--ro errors?        yang:counter64
          +--ro testframe-statistics
          |  +--ro pkts?                  yang:counter64
          |  +--ro sequence-errors?       yang:counter64
          |  +--ro payload-errors?        yang:counter64
          |  +--ro latency
          |  |  +--ro samples?   uint64
          |  |  +--ro min?       uint64
          |  |  +--ro max?       uint64
          |  |  +--ro average?   uint64
          |  |  +--ro latest?    uint64
          |  +--ro last-sequence-error
          |     +--ro timestamp?   yang:date-and-time
          |     +--ro expected?    uint64
          |     +--ro received?    uint64
          +--ro capture {capture}?
             +--ro statistics
             |  +--ro pkts?     yang:counter64
             |  +--ro octets?   yang:counter64
             +--ro frames
                +--ro frame* [sequence-number]
                   +--ro sequence-number    uint64
                   +--ro timestamp?         yang:date-and-time
                   +--ro size?              uint32
                   +--ro data?              binary
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
</t>
</section>
</section>    
<section title="Traffic Generator Module YANG" anchor="traffic-generator-module">
<t>
This module imports modules defined in <xref target="RFC8343"/> and <xref target="RFC9911"/>.
</t>
<t>&lt;CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-traffic-generator@2026-06-22.yang"</t>
        <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
module ietf-traffic-generator {
  yang-version 1.1;
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-traffic-generator";
  prefix nttg;

  import ietf-interfaces {
    prefix if;
    reference
      "RFC 8343: A YANG Data Model for Interface Management";
  }
  import ietf-yang-types {
    prefix yang;
    reference
      "RFC 9911: Common YANG Data Types";
  }

  organization
    "IETF Benchmarking Methodology Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <https://datatracker.ietf.org/group/bmwg/about/>
     WG List:  BMWG <mailto:bmwg@ietf.org>

     Author:   Vladimir Vassilev
               <mailto:vladimir@lightside-instruments.com>";
  description
    "This module contains a collection of YANG definitions for
     management of the traffic generator functionality part
     of network interconnect testers.

     Copyright (c) 2026 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
     authors of the code.  All rights reserved.

     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject to
     the license terms contained in, the Revised BSD License set
     forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).

     All revisions of IETF and IANA published modules can be found
     at the YANG Parameters registry group
     (https://www.iana.org/assignments/yang-parameters).

     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX; see
     the RFC itself for full legal notices.";

  revision 2026-06-22 {
    description
      "Initial revision.";
    reference
      "RFC XXXX: A YANG Data Model for
                 Network Tester Management";
  }

  feature multi-stream {
    description
      "The device can generate multi-stream traffic.";
  }

  feature realtime-epoch {
    description
      "The device can generate traffic precisely
       at configured realtime epoch.";
  }

  identity testframe-type {
    description
      "Base identity for all test frame types.";
  }

  identity static {
    base testframe-type;
    description
      "Indicates static test frame.
       The frame data and size are constant.";
  }

  identity dynamic {
    base testframe-type;
    description
      "Base identity for dynamic test frame.

       When used itself, it identifies unspecified
       dynamic test frame type configured outside
       of the data model specified configuration
       interface.";
  }

  identity modifier-action-type {
    description
      "Base identity for all modifier action types.";
  }

  identity increment {
    base modifier-action-type;
    description
      "Indicates increment modifier action.";
  }

  identity decrement {
    base modifier-action-type;
    description
      "Indicates decrement modifier action.";
  }

  identity random {
    base modifier-action-type;
    description
      "Indicates random modifier action.";
  }

  grouping common-data {
    description
      "Common configuration data.";
    leaf realtime-epoch {
      if-feature "realtime-epoch";
      type yang:date-and-time;
      description
        "If this leaf is present the stream generation will start
         at the specified realtime epoch.";
    }
    leaf start-delay {
      type uint64;
      units "octets";
      description
        "If this leaf is present, the traffic generation will start
         after the specified number of idle octets have elapsed.";
    }
    leaf total-frames {
      type uint64;
      description
        "If this leaf is present the traffic generation will stop
         after the specified number of frames are generated.";
    }
  }

  grouping burst-data {
    description
      "Generated traffic burst parameters.";
    leaf testframe-type {
      type identityref {
        base nttg:testframe-type;
      }
      default "nttg:static";
      description
        "In case of dynamic test frames this leaf
         can specify a derived dynamic test frame identity.
         For static test frames there is no practical use
         of derived identities.";
    }
    leaf frame-size {
      type uint32;
      units "octets";
      mandatory true;
      description
        "Size of the frames generated. For example for
         Ethernet interfaces the following definition
         applies:

         Ethernet frame-size, in octets, includes:
         * Destination Address (6 octets),
         * Source Address (6 octets),
         * Frame Type (2 octets),
         * Data (min 46 octets or 42 octets + 4 octets 802.1Q tag),
         * Frame Check Sequence (FCS) (4 octets)

         Ethernet frame-size does not include:
         * Preamble (dependent on MAC configuration
                    by default 7 octets),
         * Start of frame delimiter (1 octet)

         Minimum standard Ethernet frame-size is 64 bytes but
         generators might support smaller sizes for validation.";
    }
    leaf frame-data {
      type binary;
      description
        "The raw frame data.
         The length of the specified data can be
         shorter, then the '../frame-size' value
         specifying only the header or the header and the
         payload with or without the 4-byte FCS data
         in the case of a Ethernet frame. If the frame data string
         specified is longer, then '../frame-size' the excess
         of the specified frame data is truncated.

         In multi-stream mode, if 'frame-data' leaf for one of the
         streams is not specified, it is the value specified for
         the closest stream that precedes it that is used.";
    }
    leaf gap {
      type uint32;
      units "octets";
      mandatory true;
      description
        "Length of the period between generated frames.
         For example, for Ethernet interfaces the following
         definition applies:

         The gap between transmission of frames is the sum
         of the minimum interframe gap (IFG) as defined in
         IEEE 802.3 plus any additional idle octets plus
         the preamble (7 octets) and the start of frame
         delimiter (1 octet). A brief recovery time
         between frames allows devices to prepare for
         reception of the next frame. The minimum
         interframe gap is 96-bit times (12-octet times) (the time it
         takes to transmit 96-bits (12 octets) of raw data on the
         medium). However, the preamble (7 octets) and start of
         frame delimiter (1 octet) are considered a constant gap that
         should be included in the gap. Thus, the minimum
         value for standard Ethernet transmission should be considered
         20 octets.";
    }
    leaf burst-gap {
      type uint32;
      units "octets";
      description
        "Is similar to the gap but takes place between
         any two bursts of the stream.";
    }
    leaf frames-per-burst {
      type uint32;
      description
        "Indicates number of frames contained in a burst.";
    }
  }

  grouping modifier-data {
    description
      "Frame data modification parameters.";
    container modifiers {
      description
        "Container holding the configured modifiers list.";
      list modifier {
        key "id";
        description
          "Each modifier specifies the action to be performed
           on data at a certain offset.";
        leaf id {
          type uint32;
          description
            "Number specifying the identifier of the modifier.";
        }
        leaf action {
          type identityref {
            base nttg:modifier-action-type;
          }
          mandatory true;
          description
            "Modifier action type.";
        }
        leaf offset {
          type uint32;
          units "octets";
          mandatory true;
          description
            "Offset of the modified data of the frame.";
        }
        leaf mask {
          type binary;
          mandatory true;
          description
            "Bit mask of the actual bits affected by the modifier.";
        }
        leaf repetitions {
          type uint32;
          mandatory true;
          description
            "Count of the packets that will repeat the data before
             the modifier makes the next update.";
        }
      }
    }
  }

  grouping multi-stream-data {
    description
      "Multi stream traffic generation parameters.";
    container streams {
      description
        "A container holding the stream list.";
      list stream {
        key "id";
        description
          "Each stream repeats a burst until frames-per-stream
           count is reached followed by stream-gap delay.";
        leaf id {
          type uint32;
          description
            "Number specifying the order of the stream.";
        }
        uses burst-data;
        leaf frames-per-stream {
          type uint32;
          mandatory true;
          description
            "The count of frames to be generated before
             generation of the next stream is started.";
        }
        leaf stream-gap {
          type uint32;
          units "octets";
          mandatory true;
          description
            "Idle period after the last frame of the last burst.";
        }
        uses modifier-data;
      }
    }
  }

  augment "/if:interfaces/if:interface" {
    description
      "Traffic generator augmentations of 'ietf-interfaces'.";
    container traffic-generator {
      presence "Enables the traffic generator.";
      description
        "Traffic generator data.";
      choice type {
        mandatory true;
        description
          "Choice of the type of the generator:
           Single or multi stream.";
        case single-stream {
          uses burst-data;
          uses modifier-data;
        }
        case multi-stream {
          uses multi-stream-data;
        }
      }
      uses common-data;
    }
  }
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

<t>&lt;CODE ENDS></t>

</section>

<section title="Traffic Analyzer Module YANG" anchor="traffic-analyzer-module">
<t>
This module imports modules defined in <xref target="RFC8341"/>, <xref target="RFC8343"/>, and <xref target="RFC9911"/>.
</t>
<t>&lt;CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-traffic-analyzer@2026-06-22.yang"</t>
        <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
module ietf-traffic-analyzer {
  yang-version 1.1;
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-traffic-analyzer";
  prefix ntta;

  import ietf-interfaces {
    prefix if;
    reference
      "RFC 8343: A YANG Data Model for Interface Management";
  }
  import ietf-yang-types {
    prefix yang;
    reference
      "RFC 9911: Common YANG Data Types";
  }
  import ietf-netconf-acm {
    prefix nacm;
    reference
      "RFC 8341: Network Configuration Access Control Model";                
  }

  organization
    "IETF Benchmarking Methodology Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <https://datatracker.ietf.org/group/bmwg/about/>
     WG List:  BMWG <mailto:bmwg@ietf.org>

     Author:   Vladimir Vassilev
               <mailto:vladimir@lightside-instruments.com>";
  description
    "This module contains a collection of YANG definitions for
     management of the traffic analyzer functionality part
     of network interconnect testers.

     Copyright (c) 2026 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
     authors of the code.  All rights reserved.

     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject to
     the license terms contained in, the Revised BSD License set
     forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).

     All revisions of IETF and IANA published modules can be found
     at the YANG Parameters registry group
     (https://www.iana.org/assignments/yang-parameters).

     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX; see
     the RFC itself for full legal notices.";

  revision 2026-06-22 {
    description
      "Initial revision.";
    reference
      "RFC XXXX: A YANG Data Model for
                 Network Tester Management";
  }

  feature testframe-filter {
    description
      "Indicates that the device implements
       a filter that can specify a subset of packets to be
       analyzed as testframes.";
  }

  feature capture-filter {
    description
      "Indicates that the device implements
       a filter that can specify a subset of packets to be
       captured.";
  }

  feature idle-octets-counter {
    description
      "Indicates that the device implements
       idle-octets counter that accumulates the time
       the link is not utilized. The minimum required
       idle gaps are not counted as idle octets.";
  }

  feature capture {
    description
      "Indicates that the device implements
       packet capture functionality.";
  }

  identity testframe-type {
    description
      "Base identity for all test frame types.";
  }

  identity unspecified {
    base testframe-type;
    description
      "The configuration of the testframe
       type of the traffic analyzer is done outside of
       the data model specified configuration interface.";
  }

  identity testframe-filter {
    description
      "Base testframe-filter identity.";
  }

  identity capture-filter {
    description
      "Base capture-filter identity.";
  }

  identity bit-field-match {
    base ntta:testframe-filter;
    description
      "Bit field matching filter. Frames that do not have
       equal values for all the bits of the specified data
       at the offsets specified with bits set in the mask
       are not processed as test frames.";
  }

  grouping statistics-data {
    description
      "Analyzed traffic statistics and test frame statistics.";
    container statistics {
      description
        "A collection of interface-related statistics objects.
         The counters in this container must be initialized
         to zero when the traffic-analyzer container is created";
      leaf pkts {
        type yang:counter64;
        description
          "Total number of packets analyzed.";
      }
      leaf octets {
        type yang:counter64;
        description
          "Total number of packet octets analyzed.";
      }
      leaf idle-octets {
        if-feature "idle-octets-counter";
        type yang:counter64;
        description
          "Total accumulated period with no frame transmission
           taking place measured in octets at the current link
           speed. This counter does not increment only when the
           interface is operating at 100% of its capacity.

           Octets not counted in '../octets' but not idle are,
           for example, layer 1 framing octets - for Ethernet interfaces
           7+1 preamble octets per packet as well as the 12-octets
           minimum gap.";
      }
      leaf errors {
        type yang:counter64;
        description
          "Count of packets with errors.
           Not counted in the pkts or captured.
           For example packets with CRC error.";
      }
    }
    container testframe-statistics {
      description
        "Statistics for received testframes containing
         either sequence number, payload checksum,
         timestamp or any combination of these features.";
      leaf pkts {
        type yang:counter64;
        description
          "Total count of detected testframes.";
      }
      leaf sequence-errors {
        type yang:counter64;
        description
          "Total count of testframes with
           unexpected sequence number. After each sequence
           error the expected next sequence number is
           updated.";
      }
      leaf payload-errors {
        type yang:counter64;
        description
          "Total count of testframes with
           payload errors.";
      }
      container latency {
        description
          "Latency statistics.";
        leaf samples {
          type uint64;
          description
            "Total count of testframes used for estimating
             the latency statistics. When every testframe is
             used, samples='../pkts'.";
        }
        leaf min {
          type uint64;
          units "nanoseconds";
          description
            "Minimum measured latency.";
        }
        leaf max {
          type uint64;
          units "nanoseconds";
          description
            "Maximum measured latency.";
        }
        leaf average {
          type uint64;
          units "nanoseconds";
          description
            "The sum of all sampled latencies divided
             by the number of samples.";
        }
        leaf latest {
          type uint64;
          units "nanoseconds";
          description
            "Latency of the latest sample.";
        }
      }
      container last-sequence-error {
        description
          "Last sequence error state data.";
        leaf timestamp {
          type yang:date-and-time;
          description
            "Timestamp of the moment a testframe with
             unexpected sequence number was received.";
        }
        leaf expected {
          type uint64;
          description
            "Expected sequence number.";
        }
        leaf received {
          type uint64;
          description
            "Received sequence number.";
        }
      }
    }
  }

  grouping capture-statistics-data {
    description
      "Capture process statistics.";
    container statistics {
      description
        "Statistics for captured frames.";
      leaf pkts {
        type yang:counter64;
        description
          "Total count of captured frames.";
      }
      leaf octets {
        type yang:counter64;
        description
          "This counter is identical with the in-octets/out-octets
           counters defined in RFC8343 except that it counts the
           octets captured since the analyzer was created.";
      }
    }
  }

  grouping capture-config-data {
    description
      "Grouping with a capture configuration container.";
    container capture {
      if-feature "capture";
      presence "Enables the capture functionality";
      description
        "Contains capture parameters.";
      leaf max-frames-visible {
        type uint64;
        description
          "Maximum number of frame entries available in
           the state/capture/frames container.";
      }
      leaf max-frame-data-visible {
        type uint32;
        description
          "Maximum length of data per frame available in
           the state/capture/frames/frame/data.";
      }
      container start-trigger {
        presence "Enables trigger condition that starts
                  the capture process.";
        description
          "Specifies when the capture start is triggered.";
        choice start-trigger {
          mandatory true;
          description
            "Choice of start-trigger condition.";
          case frame-index {
            description
              "Start capturing frames at the specified frame index.";
            leaf frame-index {
              type uint64;
              description
                "First captured frame index.";
            }
          }
          case testframe-index {
            description
              "Start capturing frames at the specified
               testframe index.";
            leaf testframe-index {
              type uint64;
              description
                "First captured testframe index.";
            }
          }
        }
      }
      container stop-trigger {
        presence "Enables trigger condition that stops
                  the capture process.";
        description
          "Specifies when the capture is stopped.";
        choice stop-trigger {
          mandatory true;
          description
            "Choice of stop-trigger condition.";
          case when-full {
            description
              "Stops capturing when the implementation can not store
               more frames.";
            leaf when-full {
              type empty;
              description
                "When present in configuration capture stops when
                 the capture buffer is full.";
            }
          }
        }
      }
      container filter {
        if-feature "capture-filter";
        presence "When packets are filtered before captured
                  according to the filter type";
        description
          "Contains the filtering rules for capturing only
           a specific subset of the frames.";
        leaf type {
          type identityref {
            base ntta:capture-filter;
          }
          mandatory true;
          description
            "Type of the applied filter. External modules can
             define alternative filter type identities.";
        }
      }
    }
  }

  grouping capture-data {
    description
      "Grouping with statistics and data of one or more
       captured frames.";
    container capture {
      if-feature "capture";
      description
        "Capture statistics data and frames.";
      uses capture-statistics-data;
      container frames {
        description
          "Contains list of captured frames.";
        list frame {
          key "sequence-number";
          description
            "Statistics and data of a captured frame.";
          leaf sequence-number {
            type uint64;
            description
              "Incremental counter of frames captured.";
          }
          leaf timestamp {
            type yang:date-and-time;
            description
              "Timestamp of the moment the frame was captured.";
          }
          leaf size {
            type uint32;
            description
              "Frame length. Ideally the data captured will be
               of the same length but can be shorter
               depending on implementation limitations.";
          }
          leaf data {
            type binary;
            description
              "Raw data of the captured frame.";
            nacm:default-deny-all;
          }
        }
      }
    }
  }

  grouping testframe-config-data {
    description
      "Grouping with a testframe configuration container.";
    container testframe {
      description
        "Generated traffic burst parameters.";
      leaf type {
        type identityref {
          base ntta:testframe-type;
        }
        default "ntta:unspecified";
        description
          "The 'unspecified' default value enables the option
           for configuration of the testframe type of the traffic
           analyzer outside of the data model specified
           configuration interface.";
      }
      container filter {
        if-feature "testframe-filter";
        presence "When present packets are
                  filtered before analyzed according
                  to the filter type";
        description
          "Contains the filtering rules for processing only
           a specific subset of the frames as test frames.";
        leaf type {
          type identityref {
            base ntta:testframe-filter;
          }
          mandatory true;
          description
            "Type of the applied filter. External modules can
             define alternative filter type identities.";
        }
      }
    }
  }

  augment "/if:interfaces/if:interface" {
    description
      "Traffic analyzer augmentations of ietf-interfaces.";
    container traffic-analyzer {
      presence "Enables the traffic analyzer.";
      description
        "Traffic analyzer top container.";
      uses testframe-config-data;
      uses capture-config-data;
      container state {
        config false;
        description
          "State data.";
        uses statistics-data;
        uses capture-data;
      }
    }
  }

  augment "/if:interfaces/if:interface/ntta:traffic-analyzer/"
        + "ntta:testframe/ntta:filter" {
    when "derived-from-or-self(ntta:type, 'ntta:bit-field-match')";
    description
      "Logical AND of masked bit fields.";
    leaf mask {
      type binary;
      description
        "Specifies bit field mask for comparison.
         Non-masked bit fields are ignored.";
    }
    leaf data {
      type binary;
      description
        "Specify data to be matched according to the specified mask.";
    }
    leaf offset {
      type uint32;
      mandatory true;
      description
        "Offset in the frame.";
    }
  }
}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

<t>&lt;CODE ENDS></t>

</section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document registers two URIs and two YANG modules.</t>

      <section title="URI Registration">
<t>
IANA is requested to register the following URI in the "ns"
registry within the "IETF XML Registry" group <xref target="RFC3688"/>:
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-traffic-generator
   Registrant Contact:  The IESG
   XML: N/A; the requested URI is an XML namespace.

   URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-traffic-analyzer
   Registrant Contact:  The IESG
   XML: N/A; the requested URI is an XML namespace.
]]></artwork></figure>
</t>
      </section>

      <section title="YANG Module Name Registration">
<t>
IANA is requested to register the following YANG module in the "YANG
Module Names" registry <xref target="RFC6020"/> within the "YANG Parameters"
registry group.

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   Name: ietf-traffic-generator
   Maintained by IANA?  N
   Namespace: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-traffic-generator
   Prefix: nttg
   Reference: RFC XXXX


   Name: ietf-traffic-analyzer
   Maintained by IANA?  N
   Namespace: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-traffic-analyzer
   Prefix: ntta
   Reference: RFC XXXX
]]></artwork></figure>
</t>
      </section>
    </section>
<section title="Operational Considerations">
<t>
The configuration nodes defined in the ietf-traffic-generator module allow deterministic specification of traffic as a sequences of frames each followed by a gap. Unless 'realtime-epoch' leaf is present the interface starts generation upon the creation or any change of the configuration under '/if:interfaces/if:interface/nttg:traffic-generator'. Multiple traffic generators on different interfaces can be synchronized with the 'start-delay' leaf. Traffic generation continues until as many frames as specified by the 'total-frames' leaf when it is present are generated or until the traffic generator generator configuration under the 'traffic-generator' container is deleted causing the traffic generation to stop or changed causing the traffic generation to stop then restart.
</t>
<t>
The presence of '/if:interfaces/if:interface/ntta:traffic-analyzer' container defined in the ietf-traffic-analyzer module enables the traffic analyzer functionality on an interface. The traffic analyzer continues its operation until the 'traffic-analyzer' container is deleted or changed causing the traffic analyzer to stop then restart discarding its state including statistics and captured frames.
</t>
</section>

        <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
This section is modeled after the template described in Section 3.7.1
of <xref target="RFC9907"/>.</t>
<t>
The YANG modules “ietf-traffic-generator” and “ietf-traffic-analyzer”
define a data model that is
designed to be accessed via YANG-based management protocols,
such as the Network Configuration Protocol (NETCONF) <xref target="RFC6241"/>. These YANG-based management protocols
(1) have to use a secure transport layer (e.g., Secure Shell (SSH)
<xref target="RFC4252"/>, TLS <xref target="RFC8446"/>, and QUIC <xref target="RFC9000"/>) and (2) have to use
mutual authentication.</t>
<t>
The Network Configuration Access Control Model (NACM) <xref target="RFC8341"/>
provides the means to restrict access for particular NETCONF users to a preconfigured subset of all available NETCONF protocol operations and content.
</t>
            <section title="ietf-traffic-generator.yang">
            <t>
There are a number of data nodes defined in this YANG module that are
writable/creatable/deletable (i.e., "config true", which is the
default).  All writable data nodes are likely to be sensitive or
vulnerable in some network environments.  Write
operations (e.g., edit-config) and delete operations to these data
nodes without proper protection or authentication can have a negative
effect on network operations.  The following subtrees and data nodes
have particular sensitivities/vulnerabilities:
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>/if:interfaces/if:interface/nttg:traffic-generator: This be used for malicious purposes like generating network traffic part of a Denial-of-Service (DoS) attack.</t>
                    </list>
            </t>
            </section>
            <section title="ietf-traffic-analyzer.yang">
                <t>
Some of the readable data nodes in this YANG module may be considered
sensitive or vulnerable in some network environments.  It is thus
important to control read access (e.g., via get, get-config, or
notification) to these data nodes.  Specifically, the following
subtrees and data nodes have particular sensitivities/
vulnerabilities:

                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>/if:interfaces/if:interface/ntta:traffic-analyzer/ntta:capture/ntta:frames/ntta:frame/ntta:data: is designed for use in testing and verification but can be used
      for reading information contained in packets sent and received on any
      of the interfaces on systems that implement the capture feature
      and, thus, disclose sensitive data.
</t>
                    </list>
               </t>
            </section>
        </section>
</middle>

<back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2544'?>         
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3688'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6020'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8341'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9911'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7950'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8343'?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4252'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6241'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8040'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8340'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8446'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9000'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9907'?>

            <reference anchor="IEEE802.3-2014" target="">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE 802.3-2014</title>

          <author initials="" surname="" fullname="">
            <organization>IEEE WG802.3 - Ethernet Working Group</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2014" />
        </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="IEEE1588" target="">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE 1588-2008</title>

          <author initials="" surname="" fullname="">
            <organization>IEEE</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2008" />
        </front>
            </reference>
    </references>

<section title="Examples" anchor="examples">
    <t>
    The topology depicted in Figure 3 is used for the examples in this appendix:
        <figure>
            <name>Test setup where TG and TA modules are on distinct entities that are not colocated</name>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
    +-------------+           +------------+           +------------+
    |             | eth0 eth0 |            | eth1 eth0 |            |
    | tester0   TG|>--------->|    dut0    |>--------->|TA  tester1 |
    |             |           |            |           |            |
    +-------------+           +------------+           +------------+

            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
    </t>
<section title="Basic Test Program">
    <t>
This pseudo code program orchestrates a network test and shows how the model can be used:
      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
# Connect to network
net=connect("topology.xml")

# Configure DUTs and enable traffic-analyzers
net.node("dut0").edit( \
  "create /interfaces/interface[name='eth0'] -- type=ethernetCsmacd")
net.node("dut0").edit(
  "create /interfaces/interface[name='eth1'] -- type=ethernetCsmacd")
net.node("dut0").edit(
  "create /flows/flow[id='t0'] -- match/in-port=eth0 "
  "actions/action[order='0']/output-action/out-port=eth1")

net.node("tester1").edit(
  "create /interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/traffic-analyzer")
net.commit()

# Get network state - before
before=net.get()

# Start traffic
net.node("tester0).edit(
  "create /interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/traffic-generator -- "
  "frame-size=64 gap=20")

net.commit()

time.sleep(60)

# Stop traffic
net.node("tester1").edit("delete /interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/"
                         "traffic-generator")
net.commit()

# Get network state - after
after=net.get()

# Report
sent_pkts=delta("tester0",before,after,
  "/interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/statistics/out-unicast-pkts")

received_pkts=delta("tester1",before,after,
  "/interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/statistics/in-unicast-pkts")

analyzed_pkts=absolute("tester1",after,
  "/interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/traffic-analyzer/
  "statistics/pkts")

latency_max=absolute(after,
  "/interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/traffic-analyzer/state/"
  "testframe-stats/latency/max")

# Cleanup
net.node("tester1").edit(
   "delete /interfaces/interface/traffic-analyzer")
net.node("dut0").edit("delete /flows")
net.node("dut0").edit("delete /interfaces")
net.commit()
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
    </t>
</section>
<section title="Generating RFC2544 Test Frames">
    <t>
Appendix C.2.6.4 of  <xref target="RFC2544"/> specifies a detailed format. The 'frame-data' leaf provides an operator with full control over the generated frames payload.
Notice that the encoding used to specify the value of the 'frame-data' leaf in this pseudocode example is not the encoding NETCONF would use on the wire which is Base64 but instead it is specified with human-readable format identical to the 'hex-string' type defined in <xref target="RFC9911"/>.
      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
...
net.node("tester1").edit(
  "merge /interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/"
  "traffic-generator -- frame-data="
  "6c:a9:6f:00:00:02:6c:a9:6f:00:00:01:08:00:45:00:"
  "00:2e:d4:a5:00:00:0a:11:58:16:c0:00:02:01:C0:00:"
  "02:02:c0:20:00:07:00:1a:00:00:01:02:03:04:05:06:"
  "07:08:09:0a:0b:0c:0d:0e:0f:10:11:12")
...
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
The resulting configuration serialized as XML is shown below in Appendix A.4
    </t>
</section>
<section title="Generating Frames with Dynamic Data Fields">
    <t>
Adding a modifier functionality to the single stream traffic generator configuration.
In this example, the highest 16 bits of the source MAC address
of the generated Ethernet frame will be incremented.
      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
...
net.node("tester1").edit(
  "merge /interfaces/interface[name='eth0']/"
  "traffic-generator/modifiers/modifier[id='0'] -- "
  "offset=6 mask=ff:ff action=increment repetitions=1")
...
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
    </t>
</section>
<section title="Example: NETCONF &lt;get&#8209;config&gt; Reply" anchor="example-netconf-get-config-reply">
    <t>
This section gives an example of a reply to the NETCONF &lt;get&#8209;config&gt;
request for &lt;running&gt; for a device that implements the ietf-traffic-generator module and its configuration was modified according to the examples above.
    </t>
        <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
<rpc-reply
    xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:netconf:base:1.0"
    message-id="101">
  <data>
    <interfaces
        xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-interfaces"
        xmlns:ianaift="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:iana-if-type"
        xmlns:nttg="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-traffic-generator">
      <interface>
        <name>eth0</name>
        <type>ianaift:ethernetCsmacd</type>
        <nttg:traffic-generator>
          <frame-size>64</frame-size>
          <frame-data>
              bKlvAAACbKlvAAABCABFAAAu1KUAAAoRWBbAAAIB
              wAACAsAgAAcAGgAAAQIDBAUGBwgJCgsMDQ4PEBES
          </frame-data>
          <gap>20</gap>
        </nttg:traffic-generator>
      </interface>
    </interfaces>
  </data>
</rpc-reply>
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
</section>

</section>
</back></rfc>
